Preliminary Inventory to the Hubert Gregory Schenck papers, 1854-1960
Hoover Institution Archives
Hubert Gregory Schenck papers
1854-1960
1945-1960
50007
Hoover Institution Archives
27 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 34 envelopes, 20 albums (22.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, diaries, speeches and writings, reports, clippings, maps, and photographs relating to the Allied occupation of Japan, relations between Taiwan and the United States, and economic conditions in Japan and Taiwan.
Schenck, Hubert Gregory, 1897-1960
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1950, with increments received in 1957, 1959, 1977 and 1996.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1897 September 24 Born, Memphis, Tennessee
1916 Enlisted in the U.S. Army
circa 1916-1919 Served in the Coast Artillery Corps
1920-1921 Geologic aide, Division of Mines, Philippines
1922 A.B., geology, University of Oregon
1923 M.A., geology, University of Oregon
1924 Married Inga Bergstrom, Berkeley, California
1924-1927 Instructor, field geology course, Stanford
1926 Ph.D., geology, University of California, Berkeley
1926 Appointed to teaching staff as instructor, Stanford University
1927 Assistant professor, Stanford University
1933-1934 Advanced Fellow at the Royal Museum of Natural History of Belgium, Commission for the Relief of Belgium Educational Foundation
1935 Associate professor, Stanford University
1937-1938 Paleontologist in Iran, Afghanistan, Pakistan and India, Amiranian Oil Company
1940 Professor of Geology, Stanford University
circa 1943 Commissioned as a major in the U.S. Army, trained for Civil Affairs duties
circa 1943-1945 Served in military government posts in New Guinea, the Philippines, and Japan
1945-1951 Chief, Natural Resources Section, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Japan
1951 Promoted to colonel
1951-1954 Chief, Mutual Security Mission and Economic Cooperation Administration in Taiwan
circa 1954-1960 Returned to Stanford University on a part-time basis
1960 June 19 Died, Stanford, California
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, diaries, speeches and writings, reports, clippings, maps, and photographs relating to the Allied occupation of Japan, relations between Taiwan and the United States, and economic conditions in Japan and Taiwan.
Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers.; United States. Army; United States. Foreign Operations Administration; Asia.; Japan--Economic conditions--1945-1989.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Japan.; Military government.; Taiwan--Economic conditions.; Taiwan--Foreign relations--United States.; Taiwan.; Technical assistance, American--Asia.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Foreign relations--Taiwan.; United States--Foreign relations.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1943-1960 (Boxes 1-3)
  - Chang, T. K., Chinese Consul General in Washington, D.C., 1957 (Box 1)
  - Chutter, Reginald, 1954-55
  - Foreign government offices, China, 1954-1960
  - Foreign government offices, Japan, 1952-59
  - Ying-ch'in Ho, 1953 April 9
  - Schenck, W. E., 1952-56
  - Shen, Sampson C., 1956-58
  - Shiah, C. P., 1956-57
  - Stach, Leo W., 1955
  - General
    - 1943-47
    - 1951
    - 1952
    - 1953
    - 1954
    - 1955 (Box 2)
    - 1956
    - 1957
    - 1958 (Box 3)
    - 1959
    - 1960
- OFFICE FILES, 1945-1955 (Boxes 3-9)
  - Supreme Commander of the Allied Powers, General Headquarters, Natural Resources Section, Tokyo, Japan, 1945-1951 (Box 3-4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Conference minutes, memoranda, pamphlets, reports, and other materials.
  - Mutual Security Mission to China
    - Airgrams, circulars, dispatches, memoranda, 1952-53 (Box 5-7)
    - Narrative Industrial Progress Report, 1953 June/July (Box 8)
    - Reports, 1953
  - U.S. Foreign Operations Administration, 1954-55 (Box 9)
    Leaflets, memoranda, studies, and other materials.
- SPEECHES, WRITINGS AND RELATED MATERIAL, 1944, undated (Boxes 9-10)
  - Addresses and statements (Box 9)
  - Bibliography
  - Civil affairs, bibliography, manuscripts, articles, clippings, etc.
  - Geographic References in Harvard Libraries on Japan Proper, mimeographed report, Cambridge, 1944 (Box 10)
  - Government Organizations, Pacific Science Board, typescript
  - Natural Resources, mimeographed copy
  - Petroleum Exploration Policy in Taiwan, typescript
  - Technical Cooperation at the Crossroads, typescript
- SUBJECT FILE, 1942-1959 (Boxes 10-21)
  - Civil affairs, Philippines, report on, 1945 (Box 10)
  - Government organizations - UN educational, scientific, and cultural organizations
  - Hoover Institute and Library Program on Overseas Development - ICA/University Contract Orientation Program Report, 1955 June 25-December 31
  - Japan, 1949-1951, undated
    - Agriculture (Box 11)
    - America-Japan Society, special bulletin, 1951
    - American Institute of Crop Ecology, 1951
    - Clippings
    - Criminal statistics, 1949
    - Economy
    - Education
    - Fiscal statutes
    - Fisheries
    - Foreign affairs
    - Forestry, 1949 (Box 12)
    - History
    - Import and export statistics, 1950
    - Insurance yearbook, 1949
    - Libraries
    - Milk production
    - Miscellany (Box 13)
    - Natural resources
    - Oil production
    - Population
    - Postal services
    - Statistics
    - Toa Kenkyusho (East Asia Research Institute)
  - Key Laws, Decrees and Regulation Issued by the Axis in Occupied Europe, report by the Board of Economic Warfare, Blockade and Supply Branch, Reoccupation Division, 1942 December (Box 14)
  - Korea
  - Micronesian anthropology, interim reports of a coordinated investigation, Pacific Science Board, National Research Council, Washington, D.C., 1947-48
  - Military Government in Bangkok, Thailand - A Survey, An Estimate of the Situation, and a Plan, U.S. military report, 1943
  - National resources - conservation
  - Natural resources - population (Box 15)
  - Non-scientific organizations
  - Ryukyu Islands
  - Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, General Headquarters
    - Military Intelligence Section, General Staff, Allied Translator and Interpreter Section, Reports, 1946
    - Civil Information and Education Section, Media Analysis Division, Reports, Radio and Press Analyses, 1946 (Box 16)
  - Taiwan
    - Agriculture and livestock production
    - Alkali production
    - Aluminum production
    - Cement industry
    - Coal industry
    - Copper industry
    - Crop reporting
    - Economic development
    - Education programs
    - Electric power (Box 17)
    - Exports
    - Fertilizer industry
    - Financial statistics
    - Fisheries
    - Forestry
    - Four Year Plan
    - Highway Bureau
    - Imports
    - Industrial development
    - Industrial development (Box 18)
    - Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction
    - Limestone
    - Low-cost housing project (Keelung)
    - Monetary indices
    - Natural gas production
    - Natural resources
    - Oil production
    - Power companies (Box 19)
    - Public health
    - Railroads
    - Salt production
    - Statistics, general
    - Sugar production
    - Tea statistics
    - Textile production
    - Tobacco production
    - Trade
    - Trade (Box 20)
    - Technical Cooperation Program
  - U.S. Army, Pacific Air Command, Advanced Echelon, 1946 (Box 21)
  - U.S. Army Forces, Pacific and Allied Officers, Southwest Pacific Area, General Headquarters, Roster of Officers, 1945
  - U.S. Department of Defense, organization plan
  - U.S. Department of Interior
    - Bureau of Mines
    - General information
  - U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey (Pacific), Headquarters, 1945
  - University organizations - Institute of Marine Resources, University of California, 1959
- MISCELLANY, 1953, undated (Box 21)
  - Clippings dealing with H. G. Schencks' military, academic, and political careers (Box 21)
  - Memorabilia collected by H. G. Schenck
  - Fraleigh, Albert S., A Report on the Historical Collection of the Academia Sinica and Suggestions for Improving Its Present Condition, Taiwan, 1953 July 17
- INCREMENT, 1956-1960 (Box 22)
  General note
  Received in November 1977.
  - Bank of Taiwan, Taiwan Financial Statistics Monthly, 1960 March (Box 22)
  - Geographic terminology index cards
  - Schenck, Hubert G.
    - "Impact of Science in East Asia," reprint, Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, Volume XIV, No. 7, 1958
    - "Petroleum Exploration Policy in Taiwan,", 1957 April 30
  - Schenck, Hubert G. and Chutter, R. F.
    - "Formosan Foreign Trade and Natural Resources Development," bibliography
    - "Taiwan Trade and Natural Resources Development"
  - Taiwan Sugar (Taipei), 1960 April
  - Timoshenko, V. P., "Soviet Agricultural Policy and the Nationalities Problem in the USSR," reprint, Institute for the Study of the USSR Conference, New York, 1956 April 28-29
- MISCELLANY, 1945-1950, 1954 (Boxes 23-24)
  - Allied Powers Supreme Commander, General Headquarters. Natural Resources Section, 1945-1950
    - Press clippings, volumes 1-3, 1945-1950 (Box 23-24)
    - Correspondence in regard to the publication of Edward A. Ackerman's book Japanese Natural Resources by SCAP, Tokyo, 1950 (Box 24)
      States the position of SCAP regarding population control in Japan.
  - Allied Powers Supreme Commander, General Headquarters, Proclamations 1-3 (never used)
  - Allied Powers Supreme Commander, General Headquarters. Government Section, 1947
    Memorandum, letter, and refutation of memorandum regarding Tanzan Ishibashi and his status under SCAPIN 550, Tokyo.
  - Enomoto, Juji, "Books Used by the Japanese Navy for Teaching of International Law," Tokyo, 1945 November 30
  - Miyazaki, General S., Personal Experiences During the Solomon Campaign, 1946
  - Thomas, Elbert D., two letters, to Mr. and Mrs. Egbert Schenck, dealing with U.S. foreign policy vis-a-vis Japan, 1941, 1949
  - Raper, Arthur F., evaluation of TA program in Taiwan, Taipei, 1954
  - Wu, Kuo-Chen, letter to the National Assembly of China and four letters to Chiang Kai-Shek, 1954
- DIARIES, 1951-1953 (Boxes 25-26, 29)
  - 1951 November 12-December 31 (Box 25)
    Includes declassified records returned to file after January 2016 release by Hoover.
  - 1952 January 1-April 30
  - 1952 May 1-June 30
  - 1952 July 1-September 30 (Box 26)
  - 1952 October 1-December 31
  - 1953 January 1-April 30
  - 1953 May 1-June 30 (Box 29)
  - 1953 July 1-August 21
- U.S. Army, Far East Command, General Headquarters, Office of the Engineer, "Report of Reconnaissance of the Coronet Operation,", 1946 March 1-2 (Box 27)
- Booklets of maps of Tokyo, 1854-1861 (Box 28)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1945-1954, undated; 3,368 photos / 34 envelopes / 20 albums (Photo file, Album shelf, Oversize photo file)
  - 30 photos of agriculture in Japan, undated (Envelope A)
  - 51 photos of agriculture in Taiwan, undated (Envelope B)
  - 54 photos of fisheries in Japan, undated (Envelope C)
  - 16 photos of forestry in Japan, undated (Envelope D)
  - 15 photos of forestry in Taiwan, undated (Envelope E)
  - 37 photos of mineral resources in Japan, undated (Envelope F)
  - 26 photos of mineral resources in Taiwan, undated (Envelope G)
  - 11 photos of a crop collection project and of Japanese farmers belonging to the Omaki agricultural co-op, 1948 (Envelope H)
  - 3 photos of Mr. Norris E. Dodd, Director General of Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, 1949 March 17 (Envelope I)
    Depicts Dodd arriving in Tokyo, Japan and being greeted by Colonel Sidney L. Huff, General of the Army Douglas MacArthur, and Lt. Colonel H. G. Schenck.
  - 2 albums containing 74 photos concerning the Taiwan Ship Building Corporation, undated (Album fJ)
  - 1 album containing 153 photos of Japan, undated (Album fK)
    Relates to industrial crops, special products such as silk and cotton, soils survey and irrigation, crop collection and distribution, agricultural education and research, livestock, fertilizers, and fisheries.
  - 1 album containing 219 photos concerning Japan's agriculture, undated (Album fL)
    Relates to land reclamation and use, farming methods and equipment, food crop culture, and industrial crop culture.
  - 1 album containing 161 photos of Lt. Colonel H. G. Schenck on a Japanese whaling expedition in the Antarctic, undated (Album fM)
  - 1 album containing 76 photos of damage caused by typhoons Faye and Judith to Japanese farmlands, forests, villages, and towns, undated (Album fN)
  - 1 album containing 232 photos relating to forestry in Japan, undated (Album fO)
    Includes forest types, lumber production and utilization, flood damage and soil erosion control and forest protection and reforestation.
  - 1 album containing 135 photos of the Angaur and Ryukyus regions of Japan, undated (Album fP)
    Relates to fisheries, forestry, mining and geology, transportation, and miscellaneous industries. Also incudes photos of Lt. Colonel H. G. Schenck and his staff in Tokyo.
  - 1 album containing 155 photos relating to fisheries in Japan, undated (Album fQ)
    Depicts fishing gear, methods and vessels, marine and special products, aquiculture, fish processing, preparation and distribution, fisheries research, fisheries facilities, and whaling.
  - 1 album containing 197 photos relating to mining and geology in Japan, including their mineral resources and solid fuels, undated (Album fR)
  - 1 album containing 152 photos of oil fields, steel and iron works, chemical industries, and coal mines in Japan, undated (Album fS)
  - 1 album containing 39 photos of the reconstruction project of pier No. 10, Kaohsiung Harbor, Taiwan, completed April 1952, circa 1952 (Album fT)
  - 1 album containing 36 photos concerning a Taiwan salt factory, undated (Album fU)
  - 1 album containing 29 photos taken at Tienlun, Taiwan at the time of the inaugural ceremony of the Power Station and 9 photos taken at the Peipu Steam Power Plant, 1952 September 21-22 (Album fV)
  - 1 album containing 23 photos of Admiral Radford Party taken at Sun Moon Lake, presented by the Taiwan Power Company, undated (Album fW)
  - 1 album containing 33 photos of a pictorial review of the interconnection of the Eastern and Western Power Systems, presented to Dr. Hubert G. Schenck, Chief of ECA China Mission, by the Taiwan Power Company, 1952 January (Album fX)
  - 1 album containing 117 photos of Dr. and Mrs. H. G. Schenck while visiting the Taiwan Power Company, 1952 (Album fY)
  - 1 album containing 84 photos of a pictorial account of the Rehabilitation and Development of Telecommunication Service in Taiwan through the aid extended by the MSA under Dr. Schenck's support, undated (Album fZ)
  - 1 album containing 204 photos of the visit of Dr. Hubert G. Schenck and party to the Kaohsiung cement plant in Taiwan, undated (Album fAA)
  - 1 album containing 9 photos of Dr. Hubert G. Schenck, Chief of the MSA China Mission, visiting the Kao-Hsiung ammonium sulfate works in Taiwan, undated (Album fBB)
  - 18 photos of Dr. Hubert G. Schenck's visit to Kao-Hsiung ammonium sulfate works in Taiwan, undated (Oversize envelope mCC)
  - 30 photos of a duck netting party at the Imperial Hunting Preserve, Japan, undated (Envelope DD)
  - 80 photos concerning forestry, lead and gold mines, agricultural land, preparation of fish for the markets, and industry in Korea, undated (Envelope EE)
  - 12 photos of ruins in Manila, Philippines, 1945 March (Envelope FF)
  - 243 photos of a duck and mist netting party in Japan, undated (Envelope GG)
  - 1 album containing 65 photos of the construction of the Hsi-Lo Bridge, Yun-Lin Hsin District, Formosa, 1952 (Album fHH)
  - 9 photos of the primitive farming techniques used in Japan, 1945 (Envelope II)
  - 4 photos of Emperor and Empress Hirohito inspecting the NRS exhibit in Tokyo, 1950 (Envelope JJ)
  - 12 photos of Emperor and Empress Hirohito as they attend Arbor Day Ceremonies at Ome, Tokyo prefecture, Japan, 1948-1949 (Envelope KK)
  - 16 photos of Lt. Colonel H. G. Schenck and Governor of New York Thomas E. Dewey on a tour of Japan, 1951 July 12 (Envelope LL)
  - 8 photos of Colonel Hubert G. Schenck and dignitaries, including Herbert Hoover, 1946 (Oversize envelope mMM)
  - 7 photos of Colonel Hubert G. Schenck receiving the order of the Auspicious Star, featuring Ambassador V. K. Wellington Koo, Mrs. Ingrid Schenck Beach, and Major General W. C. Chase, Chief of MAAG (Formosa), 1954 May 28 (Envelope NN)
  - 6 photos of Colonel H. G. Schenck in an airplane fight with Mr. Nemoto, Minister of A.G. and F.O., 1951 August 8 (Envelope OO)
  - 4 photos of the Governor of Kumamoto who called on Colonel Schenck to make reports on hydro-electric power projects, 1949 December 10 (Envelope PP)
  - 9 photos of General and Mrs. Matthew B. Ridgway and party during a tour of Japan's farming communities, 1951 September 20 (Envelope QQ)
  - 10 photos of Major General Robert B. McClure as he officiated at inaugural ceremonies in Okinawa, 1950 November 21 (Envelope RR)
  - 7 photos of coal mining in Taiwan showing coal washeries, beehive cooking oven, and coal and coke transportation systems, undated (Envelope SS)
  - 30 photos of quarantine quarters and docker's living conditions, as well as new housing prepared for the dockers, Taiwan, 1953 May (Envelope TT)
  - 13 photos of damaged farmland after a typhoon in Japan, undated (Envelope UU)
  - 38 photos of Colonel H. G. Schenck presenting certificates of achievement to visiting consultants to the Natural Resources Section, Tokyo, Japan, 1951 (Envelope VV)
  - 31 photos of Colonel H. G. Schenck, Chief of the Natural Resources Section, inspecting different plants throughout Japan, undated (Envelope WW)
  - 127 photos of Mr. H. G. Schenck and Admiral Radford inspecting the Taiwan Power Plant, 1952 (Envelope XX)
  - 173 photos of Colonel H. G. Schenck's travel through Japan, undated (Envelope YY)
  - 2 photos of the launch of the Nisshin Maru, a Japanese whaling ship, undated (Oversize envelope mZZ)
  - 20 miscellaneous photos, undated (Envelope AAA)
  - 12 prints of farewell and return ceremonies of whaling expeditions in Japan, in which Hubert G. Schenck participated as Head of the Natural Resources Section, General Headquarters, Supreme Command for the Allied Powers; 2 prints of an economic mission in Japan, 1948-1949 (Envelope BBB)